Register of the John Sidney McCain Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Sidney McCain Papers
1933-1945
82114
McCain, John Sidney
5 manuscript boxes, (1.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The John Sidney McCain papers consist of correspondence, reports, dispatches, orders, and photographs relating to American naval aviation and to naval operations in the Pacific Theater during World War II. John Sidney McCain was an admiral in the United States Navy and a Commander of the Second Carrier Task Force in World War II. He was awarded Navy Cross for his heroism and the Distinguished Service Medal with two Gold Stars for exceptional service
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1884 August 9 Born, Carroll County, Mississippi
1901-1902 Student, University of Mississippi
1906 Graduate, U.S. Naval Academy, Commander, ensign, U.S. Navy
1920 Graduate, Naval War College
1935-1936 Flight instructor (naval aviator), Naval Air Station, Pensacola, Florida
1937-1939 Commanded the aircraft carrier Ranger (CV-4)
1939 Served as Commander of Air Forces for Western Sea Frontier and the South Pacific Force
1941 Promoted through grades to Rear Admiral
1943 July Promoted to Vice Admiral
1942 September - 1943 July Chief, Bureau of Aeronautics
1943 July Deputy Chief, naval operations for air, Commander, Carrier Task Force
1943 August Rose to the rank of Vice Admiral as Deputy Chief of Naval Operations
1944 Returned to the Pacific Theater as Commander of the Fast Carrier Task Force Earned the Navy Cross
1945 Awarded the Distinguished Service Medal with two Gold Stars for outstanding performance as an air planner and carrier task force commander and awarded the Navy Cross for gallantry
1945 September 2 Witnessed the Japanese surrender on board U.S.S. Missouri
1945 September 6 Died, Carrollton, Mississippi Posthumously appointed Admiral effective that date
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of John Sidney McCain, acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982, deal with United States naval aviation and naval operations in the Pacific theater during Second World War.
The papers have been organized into three series. Correspondence includes letters, of a both official and personal nature, with names of some prominent correspondents mentioned and arranged chronologically. The United States Navy File covers air distribution lists, dispatches, orders, and operating procedures relating to American naval operations particularly in the Pacific region. Last but not the least are the photographs divided by the creator generally into groups including the date, the location, and the names of photographers.
The original order of the McCain papers has been maintained and security- classified documents have been pulled out of the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 3 series: Correspondence, United States Navy File, and Photographs
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
United States. Navy--Aviation.; United States. Navy. Carrier Task Force, Second; United States. Navy--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1933-1945
  Personal and official correspondence sent to and received from John Sidney McCain, arranged chronologically. Includes correspondence with C. M. Austin, M. M. Dupre, L. B. Porterfield, John N. Towers, and others. Also includes memoranda and related materials.
  - 1933-1934 (Folder 1: 1)
  - 1935-1940. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes correspondence with C. M. Austin, M. M. Dupre, L. B. Porterfield, W. C. I. Stiles, Zane Thompson, Jr., M. J. Torlinski, and others
  - 1939-1941. (Folder 1: 3)
    Letters to John H. Towers. See also folder 7
  - 1940-1942. (Folder 1: 4)
    Includes correspondence with Robert L. Ghormley, H. F. Leary, G. L. Roberts, and John H. Towers
  - 1941 January-December (Folder 1: 5)
  - 1942 April-September (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1942 January - 1945 August. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes correspondence with John H. Towers. See also folder 3
  - 1943 October - 1944 August (Folder 1: 8)
- United States Navy File, 1941-1945
  Correspondence, dispatches, Fast Carrier Task Force instructions, operating orders and procedures, and war diary, arranged alphabetically and then in chronological order
  - Action reports, 1944 October 29 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Aircraft Scouting Force
    - 1939 June - 1941 November (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1941 January - 1942 April (Folder 1: 11)
  - Subject file., See also Photographs
    - Dispatches REF Storm, 1944 December 15-22 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Operation orders I-44 and 2-44, 1944 August-September and undated. (Folder 2: 2-3)
      Includes standard operating procedures, undated
    - Task Force 38 operations, 1945 January 25 (Folder 2: 4)
    - War diary - Roster of daily activities, 1944 August 18 - 1945 July 31. (Folder 2: 5)
      Includes 12 photographic prints taken in Formosa, Japan, Philippines, and Russia
  - United States Pacific Fleet
    - Fast Carrier Task Force instructions, 1944-1945 and undated (Folder 3: 1)
  - Second Carrier Task Force and Commander Task Force 38
    - Undated. (Folder 3: 2)
      Air support plan in support of bombardment groups, distribution list, strategic targets - Tokyo, and map. Operation orders 2-45 and 3-45
    - 1944 February - 1945 June. (Folder 3: 3)
      Thirty Eight, operation order 2-45
    - 1944 October 2-29. (Folder 3: 4)
      Commander Task Group 38 Point One Action Report. Includes 6 photographic prints taken in the Philippine Islands
    - 1944 November 13 - 1945 January 1. (Folder 3: 5)
      Communication plan numbers 2-45
    - 1945 July 2-August 15. (Folder 3: 6)
      Includes 1 photographic print taken in Tokyo area
    - 1944 December - 1945 August 22. (Folder 4: 1)
      Commander Task Force 38 Action Report. Includes 2 photographic prints, 1944 December 5, taken in Japan
    - 1945 June 7. (Folder 4: 2)
      Includes 11 photographic prints generally of individuals taken in the Pacific area
    - 1945 July-August. (Folder 4: 3-4)
      Includes copies of photographs
- Photographs, 1939-1946
  Photographs of bombing of Japan, Luzon Islands, Manila Bay, Second Carrier Task Force, shipping damage, Sibuyan sea battle, and miscellaneous prints, arranged chronologically. Names of photographers, often names of ships, have been mentioned whenever available
  - Shipping damage, 31 photographic prints, 1944 January 3-December 14 and undated (Folder 4: 5)
    Photo by U.S.S. Cowpens, U.S.S. Hornet, U.S.S Franklin, U.S.S Hancock, U.S.S. Ticonderoga, and U.S.S. WASP, U.S. Navy
  - Second Carrier Task Force, 1944 January 3 - 1946 October 10 and undated. (Folder 4: 6)
    25 prints photographed by U.S.S. Cowpens, U.S.S. Essex, U.S. Navy
  - Bombing of Japan depicted in 36 prints, 1944 October 10 - 1946 October 16 and undated. (Folder 4: 7)
    Includes greetings sent to John S. McCain on his birthday and anniversary, 1945, August 9
  - Sibuyan sea battle depicted in 3 prints, 1944 October 24 (Folder 5: 1)
    photographed by U.S.S. Franklin, U.S. Navy
  - Luzon Islands, Philippine Islands, 1944 October 25 - 1945 January 12 (Folder 5: 2)
    photos by U.S.S. Franklin and U.S.S. Ticonderoga, U.S. Navy. 16 prints
  - Manila Bay depicted in 6 prints, 1944 November 5 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Miscellaneous prints, 1944 January - 1945 September (Folder 5: 4)
    photographed by U.S.S. Navy and U.S.S. Shangrila, U.S. Navy. 28 prints